[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome everybody to the stoa the stoa
is a place
for us to cohere and dialogue at the
knife's edge
of what matters most at this very moment
i'm nick benjamin
your host for this third session with
sensemaker and resident zach stein
who has so far presented his
metapsychological framework
to shed light on the psyche so
another word on the structure zack's
presentation
will be followed by a q a
just write your questions in the chat
unmute yourselves when i call on you to
ask your question
because this is being put on youtube if
you want me to ask your question for you
just say so in the chat
so without further ado zack stein take
it away
hey everybody it's a gorgeous autumn day
in vermont it got down to like 30 last
night so there was
a pretty intense frost uh so i'm sitting
in the sun because
basically there's only a few weeks left
of it and then there'll be no sun so i'm
so getting it in
so so i am going to
run through the final bit of slides as
promised
and then move into probably a more
extended
q a with the hope of bringing some
substantive problems
to the table so not questions about the
model
but questions about the world that we
can use the model to
to grapple with and handle so that's
where we'll be going
um let me share my screen here
okay so first i'll just uh
as they say recapitulate so that we're
all
roughly on the same page here so you
remember we were working in the
kind of liminal space between the
sciences of psychology and
metaphysics and philosophy and moving
from charles sanders purse we opened up
into this
triplicate of metapsychology of
transcendence
insolent development
these move through different kinds of
transformation
stages stations phases and there's a
kind of
relationship between these higher order
parts
so we move through installment as you'll
recall uh
symbols are not images um
and insolent is a process that
involves the intensification elaboration
of image as such we looked at
development
we remember now that development is
messy
right the development's not a simple
ladder it's not simple growth to
goodness
that there's a tremendous amount of
complexity
multiple lines moving through levels
and then also webs of development
dynamical systems types of phenomenon
with differences between
functional and optimal level spreads
between different competing growers
within the self
micro development macro development
different time cycles different
uh dynamics of interpersonal
relationships
so we moved beyond a simple notion of
development and then we kind of like put
that in relation to this
notion of installment and now we want to
move into the discussion of
transcendence basically and
then rap um uh
so you know i started installment with
hillman
but there could have been other pictures
there right there's other theorists
and practitioners of insolent of course
uh
and began development with psja in part
just because i had that desk
picture just the disorganized desk
picture which i picked that psja picture
because there could have also been
baldwin or
or other folks there so i put maslow
here
uh abraham maslow because
he touched uh and brought into the
cultural consciousness
the notion of self-transcendence
and transcendent experiences and peak
experiences there's a recent book out by
scott barry kaufman
just called transcend where he
kind of resuscitates some of maslow's
thinking so it's a pretty good book i'm
not going to speak to but i wanted to
bring into the
into the room abraham maslow because
we're going to be looking at
transcendence not
in a let's say simple
uh kind of let's for lack of a better
term buddhistic way
right transcendence has a lot more
to do with uh life as it is lived in
relationship and in the world
than is the normal um
kind of connotation of that word and so
maslow with his notions of
self-transcendence touched across a
wider spectrum of ways of
engaging with transcendence as a
modality aside from just like stopping
thought
and opening consciousness and
transcending self
there's a lot more to the notion of
transcendence as we'll get into
so the triple within the triple dribbles
within triples within triples
uh it's just symbol attention
consciousness
uh modalities of the modality
um and the notion of phases
uh so you remember that
development moved through stages and
probably these are the most
commonly understood uh of the three
um the pgiden stages the goldbergian
stages the wilburian stages the spiral
dynamics stages keegan stages lavender
stages right so there's stages
everywhere
stations i introduced as a notion within
insolent which is
less well worked up but it has been
worked up
and there we saw like pre-tragic tragic
post-tragic as a form of stages um
excuse me stations
um and so phases is is different
um so this isn't phase like he's going
through a phase like adolescence that's
not what this is
this is phases like in the notion of
chaos theory
that very complex dynamical systems go
through
phase transitions or phase shifts which
move relatively abruptly from one
let's say a tractor or basin to another
attractor or basin
and so that's the way i like to model
the dynamics
of transformation within transcendence
is you don't go through stages you don't
go through
stations you move through
phases and so we're going to talk a
little bit about that
and these phases have to do with
essentially the way consciousness
constellates around the process of
symbolization
right and so we discussed images at some
length and kind of talked about the way
that you can
extract universal symbols from within
the texture of unique images
and when we were in the discussion of
installment i was kind of saying let's
stick with the image
and not go off and up into the universal
symbol although that's possible and
important
from the perspective of transcendence
the whole point is in fact
to engage in the process of
symbolization with
life itself to pull everything up and
into
the universal self-transcending symbol
it's the process of symbolization
so precisely from the image you take the
symbol
if you're working the modality of the
transcendent
and so this brings us to this notion
that you find in the work of robert j
lifton who's a fascinating psychologist
he interviewed uh the survivors of
hiroshima
and he interviewed people who went
through uh
communist re-education camps and formal
types of brainwashing uh so he was
interested in the kind of
extremities of human experience
specifically in the engagement
with kind of like unlimited
technological
violence and uh death or annihilation
specifically like absurd death or
surreal death
anyway there's a lot to say about
lifton's work but this notion of
symbolic immortality
uh is one of the things that you can
kind of contribute to the field and it's
directly in this
area of transcendence he posited that
essentially
there's a experience of continuity
with life with history and with reality
that is a basic human need that there's
some essential process
of symbolization during which you
from your experience uh
basically draw yourself up and into a
form of symbolic immortality that this
is like a like mental hygiene like if
you're doing a good job
you should have a rich sense of your own
symbolic immortality
and it happens in different ways like it
can be through your biological line
like for a long time humans had a sense
of
symbolic immortality by imagining their
continuity through
ancestry and then into the future of
those people who are
part of their their line uh symbolic
immortality is
through a sense of having a place in
history connection with cultural past
noting how your contribution let's say
your
actions or writing will move into the
future of
culture so you feel symbolic immortality
connection with the full kind of
historicity of human experience and then
of course
the experience of continuity with nature
with consciousness itself
um with the universal patterns of
the cosmos that these things can be
metabolized as part of your psyche
in the modality of transcendence
and the healthy forms of symbolization
bring us up and into symbolic
immortality
right now if you have an experience like
let's say two world wars
and the onset of
atomic potential atomic annihilation
self-inflicted extinction of the species
lift and posits that it uh
disrupts the normal process of imagining
your symbolic immortality
so i'm going to return to this but
basically
[Music]
whereas the soul orients to death you'll
recall and i can speak more to that
the transcendent orients to immortality
and precisely because the sense of
cultural
and historical continuity has fractioned
and the sense that the future isn't
possible that capitalism can't imagine
its own
immortality means that we have cut
ourselves off from
the sense of continuity with history and
that our
works and actions will survive in
perpetuity
and so there's been a retreat towards
those forms of symbolic immortality that
have to do with
altered consciousness right and so we
equate transcendence with
altered consciousness which when allows
us to experience
you know thankfully allows us to
experience continuity with
things like nature or reality itself
but there's a paucity of healthy
symbolization
around um uh transcendence through
engaging with
civilization history uh life on earth
biological life
um so there's kind of three uh
classic paths this is kind of my
summation of a lot of the work on
transcendence moving beyond lifton's
work but
but including liftman's work
to uh to feel those forms of continuity
with life and with history
uh and with reality that we can
metabolize and
symbolize into our own experience of
transcendence
right symbolic mortality as it were um
so meditation is the one uh most
i think that says mediation not
meditation but that's so that could be a
typo there
um so uh so
meditation and theodren's or you know
drugs for lack of a better term and
service and care
um and so it's important to get that the
notion of transcendence isn't just
the one that's held within the
meditation traditions
um that uh
this does give us that sense of
continuity with
uh let's say life itself consciousness
or reality
it also allows us to release the
kind of identity beyond the skin
encapsulated
ego which is another property of
transcendence and actually
often time and other things will float
away so the experience of
being immortal or timeless in the moment
is possible with meditation practice
but it's not just that and it's not also
strictly speaking related to altered
states of consciousness let's say
induced through
entheogens which also can kind of
speed up and it and and concentrate
these processes of symbolization
uh and experiences symbolic immortality
uh but this was one of maslow's points
that many forms of peak experience
and self-transcendence have to do with
forms of service and care where you
essentially
find an altar upon which you sacrifice
your ego and through that experience
the transcendence of self and actually
the continuity with life
and with history and with the species
that are the stuff that allows you to
to feel through symbolic connection to
uh more than yourself to immortality
um and so you know
when you look at the way
anthogens in particular in contemporary
culture have been hypertrophied as
a medium of transcendence
it speaks to the point i raised with
lifton about the
lack of ready availability for
symbolic immortality which is to say
that
if we can't if we can't imagine a future
for our own civilization
and we sometimes can't even imagine a
future for the biosphere itself
at least the biosphere as we know it
then the prospect of attempting to find
symbolic immortality by attaching to a
particular
culture or place or nation
becomes difficult right
and when the information ecology is so
fractured that you can't get a sense of
what those things would even mean like
what does the united states even mean
who are these guys right when you when
you can't
figure uh out how to connect you're the
substance of your identity
to a symbolic structure that's larger
than itself that's a part of history and
humanity
then you find transcendence through
another
means which isn't invalid but it is
a way of uh in the sense of relieving
the construct of identity
from its uh responsibility to history
and attempting to find transcendence by
kind of a radical uh a historical
immersion within consciousness as such
or reality as
such and
so what you find in in these practices
is a
is a couple things one is that uh
massively impactful and valid
symbolization processes do take place
so like symbolization as lifton
describes as i'm working with it here
this process of metabolizing experience
into universal symbol which you
are identified with and therefore
feeling the sense of immortality
that you can get that form of identity
transformation
but it's worth noting there are let's
say
endogenous means by which these
same forms of transcendence can be
induced
we'll talk about meditation later but we
can also talk about the other forms of
peak experiences
and so when you think about what we
talked about with development
and you think about how delicate the
developmental skill web is
as it dynamically moves through the
levels of development
you also have to think about the impact
of certain practices of transcendence
let's say drugs
on development and in soulman right
so exogenous forms of transcendence
inducing
symbolization may disregulate
certain forms of complex skill
development
and complicated installment processes as
well
so you have to think about the full
range of dynamic
impact you know when you're working
in let's say um
using extreme measures to impact any one
of the three modalities
right uh and so that's my
kind of like brief uh
brief overview of these questions so yes
like
this is a historically uh
you know tons of historical precedent
for the use of entheogens
in inducing transcendence and symbolic
immortality
but caution
so this is a lorenz attractor and so
this is what i'm talking about with
phase shifts
and entheogens are probably the one
that's that everyone or
many people have experienced where it's
like okay
ten minutes later that's different right
uh and it was abrupt and in fact
you are now in a new world right and so
the same thing happens when you fall
into a depressive episode
you're like oh [ __ ] that week went by
and now i'm here
and as wittgenstein says you know the
world is different to
the depressed man
and so that notion that yeah
consciousness itself
actually moves through phase shifts
uh in a profound manner that affect your
ability to
to symbolically metabolize your
experience
it affects your ability to hold
attention and affects the like
taste or quality of
consciousness and then of course that
propagates through development and
insulting across the different
modalities
and so that notion of yes phase shift
so this is one of those first books that
came out looking at like the
neuroscientific effects of meditation
but similar to enthiogens is that notion
that you can
through a specific kind of practice
engage intentionally not by accident
like with depression or something you're
intentionally engaging a phase shift
in the nature of awareness consciousness
and
the symbolic immortality
so this is the default mode network
which is where a lot of convergence is
happening around
neuroscience uh research for mindfulness
and
mystical states and altered states of
consciousness what's interesting about
the default network is that it is
actually recruiting
uh basically those parts of the brain
that have to do with
your place in time and space
so like if you were trying to figure out
how to get out of a building
and you were imagining all the paths out
of the building and where you would be
you would
you recruit the default network uh
anyway so there's a lot to say about it
but
the reason i put this in here is that
the other misunderstanding about
transcendence is that like you leave
your body
or something like that or that the body
is not important in transcendence
or but in fact uh as steiner said
uh you know heaven is in your bones
that transcendent of all the three
modalities
the transcendent one is in fact the
location of
quote unquote embodiment practice right
that the transcendent is the body and so
through choice and action you'll
remember maybe in the first lecture i
talked about the transcendent has having
to do with action
and choice and actually joining the
causal
unfolding of the universe putting your
cause in
to the causal unfolding of the universe
so it's that
notion where your body hits other bodies
and where your body is and takes up
space a unique space
so that is true meditation is true of
emphyogens these are these are
physiological processes that meditation
is not a process of leaving your body
it is in a fat it is in fact a process
of being the body
um and so the default network uh
kind of shows that it like so in
meditation
in uh in certain forms of
hypnagogic state etc the way the brain
itself
models the body becomes the kind of
gateway to the quote-unquote experience
of losing
the body mind-body drop as they call it
in zen
delta wave activity
eventually dream state etc so these are
advanced transcendental meditation
practitioners
2007 that's a really dope geodesic dome
and they are all meditating and they did
this for i think some
years to attempt to reduce
violence um and uh
according to their statistics it worked
right
so i'm not going to go into all of that
um
but uh it is interesting
to think about and when you look at
specifically patterns of
[Music]
behavior in prisons and schools and
other places
it's clear that something's going on
here
when you get a groups of people
engaging in transcendence practices
together uh
so again i'm not gonna get into all that
but there's a lot
of research that needs to be done there
because i think that this was something
that was very
common part of human experience for an
extremely long time
and now is something that like when
people look at this picture there's two
reactions one is like oh that's amazing
i'd love to go meditate and the other
one's like that's a creepy cult like
that's a weird creepy cult what are they
doing
right and so like that sense of
we are um
uh almost more averse to transcendence
or kind of fetishizing transcendence
uh specifically around symbolization and
then bringing death in with insulin like
this is the cluster of problems for a
society that's complicated
like when freud was writing the clusters
of problem that were complicated had to
do with like sexuality and stuff
but now the clusters of problems that we
need to worry about have to do with
death and symbolic immortality
that the ubiquitous presence of kind of
unlimited technological
violence and potentiality for kind of
quote absurd
death which is to say meaningless death
the and the at the inability or the
deadening which stops
the symbolization towards symbolic
immortality
that these are the things that are
constricting the psyche and causing
neurosis pathology psychosomatic
symptomology not
sexuality not that there isn't problems
in our culture with sex believe me there
is
but compared to victoria in england or
something when freud is writing
uh it's it's quite different um uh so
they're related and i'm not saying we
it's the sexual once solved but i'm
saying that with
especially after the nuclear bomb and
you get into the
context of ecological disaster and you
start having
in the public awareness images
in the insolment sense images of
self-induced extinction
limiting the context in which symbolic
immortality can be expressed and
experienced
then you start to have a strange dynamic
almost repressed
relationship to these modalities of
transcendence where you'll either over
fetishize them
or you will fear them
and so the other one you'll remember is
care that the other way
to engage in the transcendent modality
is to be in the body but not in a state
of
entheogenic altered consciousness
or meditative quiescence and autonomic
autonomic nervous system like
realignment through meditation
but in an engagement uh
with others in the context where
there is a real need uh
that must be met uh
that can only be met through your let's
say unique
uh position and ability to be there
and so this is a very important
thing to recognize about the human
psyche that in fact
we experience transcendence right it's
not like being on drugs or like
meditating it's a different experience
but we
find substance for symbolizing our own
immortality through doing good works for
others not in the abstract like
but like touching them helping them
giving
uh in the flesh and
you know whenever i speak with someone
who has experienced depression
and anxiety i'll often say uh
find a way to
[Music]
to do service work like it's one of the
best cures
it's finding a way to literally actively
engage in
in caring for others um
and so maslow noted this too that there
was an inordinate number of people who
had their kind of like peak experiences
like kind of like god consciousness
experiences
in the context of what's kind of a
situation of duress
where they are kind of like caring for
someone who's in immediate need
so that's just worth noting as an
element of transcendence and so
this can be your own work the altar on
which you sacrifice yourself can be
your work you can you can find symbolic
immortality through
works that one would be saved through
works right that notion like
that it is as real an experience in the
psyche as
um you know meeting god on dmt
or uh having you know pure buddha
consciousness through meditation
so
all right so we're going to wrap so we
had these
three modalities they went through these
kinds of transformations
what i want to do here is show that
these are all related in a very complex
way
and in fact it is the case that each of
them
can enfold into the others so let me
i mentioned this last time but i want to
deepen it now so
if you move through certain stages of
development you can get to certain
capacities which open
certain stations right
you move through certain stations you
can get through you can get into certain
positions that allow for certain
phases of consciousness to change all
right so that's an example of one way of
running it
so i'm going to move quickly but i think
you might be able to follow me here
similarly
and this is talked about a lot if you
can intentionally induce
phase shifts in your own consciousness
let's say if you become a really good
meditator
that can open the doorway for more rapid
acquisition of
stage development in skill structure
right
and etc so this becomes a really
interesting kind of matrix
where you can look at how uh okay let's
imagine i'm
pretty tragic tragic post-tragic right
now i became a post-tragic person at a
young age
because some [ __ ] went down so now i'm
up in post-tragic
that actually prepares me to have access
to certain phase shifts in my
consciousness and awareness that
are unique because i'm all the way up at
that station at a young age
those phase shifts could allow me to dig
into certain
types of skill development right so
that's so you can start to see how you
can use the model
to give different kinds
of um let's say advice
or it wields different forms of
self-understanding
uh so these are all related i'm not
going to run through all the iterations
um but uh hopefully when i sit down to
try to write this thing out i'll
i'll start to get some of that going uh
and then again the
the rotation between them goes in this
direction
and insolent is root in many ways
but depending on where you're at you can
start this rotation
at any one of those positions um and i'm
not going to get into that but you can
imagine for example if someone
already has a deeply developed skill set
in a particular area
that they took on almost unreflectively
as a part of their schooling
that's starting with that highly
developed skill set and figuring out a
way to pull from it
some form of meaning into the
transcendence to position then a new
image of the self to re-motivate
right so you can move around the circle
starting in any position and so if you
know landry's
metaphysics what you'll find in here is
the paths
all right so that
is the entire slide deck
and i will post this on my
website uh so that it will be available
um so from here on out it is basically
q a or kind of workshop style
and um you know if there are things that
are just too conf like so confusing you
feel like you can't
move on that we will answer those
questions but as i said i think
an interesting thing to think through
would be you know what are some things
that are you're grappling with in the
world
that you have an inkling like oh what
zach just said like that could help me
make sense of that what
what does that look like to apply the
model um
so that's that's where i'll leave it and
then of course next week the whole thing
will just be
will just be open for us to for us to
talk
thank you zach um so i guess i i'd love
to start us off with a question
john verbaki talked about neoliberalism
as a kind of
zombie ideology post 2008 just
heedlessly moving toward extinction
because we're in the system
every day our actions cannot help but
supported self-perpetuation
my psyche interprets that as a a
moving moving helping civilization move
towards extinction towards death
so in what way does our relationship
with death in the west
need to change in order to lay the
groundwork for a healthier
installment
yeah i mean it's interesting right if i
run
the metapsychology on the culture
uh then what you get is actually an
obvious over
focus on certain forms of technical
skill development
right like neoliberalism did some [ __ ]
extremely well
it was just very short-sighted and
eventually running a self-terminating
pattern
um but there were certain technical
lines of development
certain ways of objectifying the world
of extracting raw materials of
processing the materials
global supply chain inter connection
just in time
shipping so you didn't have to warehouse
and you could just link everything up
through getting things there just in
time like all of that stuff
uh i mean you know come on uh
but then when you look at how is it
relating to the other modalities
um that's where it gets a little
actually dark and twisted
and i already mentioned lifton's notion
that
you know post-world war ii the culture
of the entire planet was more or less
reeling from the shock of existential
risk that for the first time we had
unlimited technological violence to the
extent that we could destroy
we could wipe biological life from the
from the mantle
of the earth and uh and for a brief
period of time that was like oh okay the
cold wind had mutually assured
destruction
but you'll notice now we've kind of
settled into
just living with that and a lot of that
began which is to say the normalization
of ecocide and impending
catastrophic or existential risk the
normalization of that
required a numbing to the other
modalities
of insolent and transcendence so while
we were and this is a classic pattern
individual development
while you're working really hard to
build those skills to make a lot of
money
neoliberalism you are ignoring
the ways you are symbolizing your own
immortality and you are ignoring the
images in which you're trafficking that
are basically insolent you or bringing
you down and into
social relationships uh
so in that to that extent it's like um
could some of the kind of like
technological
and kind of like skill structure
architecture of neoliberalism have
developed
in a container of transcendence and
insolent that was actually
much more reasonable perhaps
we would have a working global order or
something like that
like that's possible right like if we're
going to survive we need a planetary
planetary order that actually works
that's not self-terminating so how do
you do that is it just a technical
problem
is it that neoliberalism actually was
just a technical mistake they didn't
actually figure out
how to you know get the markets balanced
and get the right
green technologies and that stuff is it
just a technical problem
in the domain of development or is there
some dynamic actually of insulin and
transcendence that humanity must go
through
to balance that skill set um
so that's me taking your question kind
of up and into the metapsychological
lens but you'll find in there things
that
come from a bunch of scholarly
traditions you know
um polanye and habermas you know
said as much the kind of like running
wild of objectifying instrumental reason
to the deficit of those forms of
practical
uh reason having to do with you know
communicative action
and values and things of that nature so
there's many ways to tell that story i
just told
cool thank you thank you
rob hart has a bunch of questions
do you want us to mute yourself sure
i had one question that was more about
culture which i
i feel like you may have just answered
and one that's more about transcendence
and meditation for the individual which
would you prefer we
whatever you want man um i'm leaning
toward culture
actually so i i asked do you see the
current ascendancy of celebrities and
political tribes as a collective attempt
to treat leaders and tribes as symbols
and images of transcendence and
and are we replacing religion and
mythology with these collective
narratives
if so is there any upside to that is it
sustainable possibly and
where does it lead psychologically for
the individual and for the collective
yeah that's interesting uh
so celebrity culture is definitely
best read through that
model of something like
symbolization so
the celebrity lives an image right and
most of our celebrities are in fact
uh craft their image
right so they're they're they seduce you
through image creation uh and
but the but the real punch is in
the process of symbolization on top of
that image creation
so what you end up having is the cult of
personality which makes that person
more than a person right
so that's that's a deep dynamic which i
think when you read it
that way when you read it that someone
creates basically ritual
creates image positions themselves
to be the one who is the stuff you
metabolize during the process of
symbolization
right to connect your own symbolic
immortality
to a symbol larger than you right so
it's like an old school
psyops that humans have been running
since they've been creating culture
tribes right
um where you you create the image and
then you sit in the throne and then you
can't but be
symbolized as the king archetype and
then the whole thing
constellates in the dynamic right
and so that's what's so kind of like uh
that's why like when rock and roll came
out and people like it's the devil's
music
like there is something that is
strangely
captivating at a soul level about the
archetypal constellations that
are produced through pop culture
[Music]
so what that means is that there's way
more
way more intense cathexis as fredwood
said emotional investments specifically
of the transcendent type
in the celebrity personality which
means that the um
the well say a few things you're saying
what's the flip side of that one is that
you get
the equivalent of living god which means
that like
if someone plays it right
and in adolescence they're able to get
up and out of
the idealization that they were stuck in
let's say of a sports figure
they can realize that okay that guy
isn't that ideal
right he's a human he's a person but
this ideal of like someone who
works hard and and makes it makes enough
money because he deserves it and
like positive attributes of the ideal
those things are just hugely important
and a part of teacherly authority
right and so i think this is what many
celebrities kind of hope that they're
doing
is that they're allowing kids to see an
ideal that they could potentially strive
for or something like that but in order
for that to work you have to be able to
just attach to the ideal from the
particular
human put them back in their unique
image with all of its
messiness and and not use them as a as a
symbolizing process or do so consciously
so the flip side is that if you see
someone as a superhero when you're
growing up
uh and you can mature out of the
adolescent identity crisis and then
take that image and throw it out in
front of yourself and move towards it as
your own ideal
instead of keeping it embodied in them
that could be positive but my sense is
that
first of all many of the things that
people idealize celebrities for are not
positive traits
and second of all the there's a ceiling
on the culture which
postpones or actually completely negates
the possibility of resolving adolescent
identity crisis
which means that you never get the
figure ground shift to pull the ideal
back
from the father mother celebrity
king god ideal superhero thing
and then you end up living resentfully
in the shadows
of the forms of authority
and virtue and capacity you couldn't
acquire for yourself
um so there's a real difficulty in
saying that anything that's happening
with
popular culture with the celebrity
culture is positive
i would say mostly they've they've ended
up
again using really old
hardware software of the of the psyche
to create these images for the
symbolization process
for you know a very serious soul level
and capture of symbolic immortality
processing
so yeah so i'm not sure if any of that
made sense
but but i think it i think it might be
helpful
junita you had a question
uh hey hi mike i'm trying to
understand something about my own kind
of mapping
of your of your work so maybe you could
help me like i'm really confused so like
the transcendence
and the installment they seem to be
deep timeless structures of the human
condition
i mean you know me this could be my
allergies so just call me out
the development seems like a little ad
hoc
like it seems it seems
um like it's not in the same stature of
the other two it seems like a
kind of divergent more of an
epistemological move of modernity
let's say like i don't see them as uh
at the same status and and so
for example um i would say
that so where does insolent the process
of installment
stop and development begins like
like um and this is because i'm
i'm thinking of development as
hierarchical complexity
right and maybe that's the problem
do you understand my question it's like
it's like insomnia is timeless
and and transcendence is timeless
but developmental stage growth
is it is it is it also timeless
this is an interesting thing totally no
i hear what you're saying
uh well a few responses one would be
that
transcendence is definitely timeless
i don't insolent definitely has to do
with temporality
um and moves towards okay so let me let
me just clarify i don't mean timeless
like
it doesn't move but it's always been
part of the human condition
correct yeah it has development
yes you you are describing always been
part of the human condition
okay and so then what do we mean by
development hierarchical complexity
uh no i mean so what i mean by about so
and this is where this is why it is
worth putting psja on that slide
but you could also look at michael
tomasello's work or anyone who's looked
at
basically the way the nervous system of
monkeys and children
works with the physical environment
before there's any
language or culture or anything
and then when humans are a distinctly
cultural species which is to say the
species-specific trait
has to do with a certain form of
intersubjectivity
and culture and teaching and learning i
think
so the model of hierarchical complexity
is a particularly
useful lens on that process
which humans and animals have been doing
for as long as they've been
trying to operate effectively on the
physical world basically
and that's so that's not installment for
you that's
already development that's that's
development
correct yeah i think that's because my
semantic mapping like for me that's
in some installment the process of
installment but anyways i got
that's so now that makes sense to me but
it was more like semantic mapping but
then i'm
very curious about
is the layer of image
and specifically the image of self
and world that's layered basically on
top of or
within that developmental engagement
with the world
so it's like you know
and this is where the you know do
animals have souls
the animals go through insolent the
human like so it gets really complicated
but basically you know when that
first so the k that's this is like i'm
making up like a russoian
like fiction of nature when the caveman
you know who has figured out how to live
with other cavemen and do things
start to have an image and
maybe even begin to share that image
among themselves about the meaning of
that activity
that they're participating and let's say
when they start to bury one another
uh then you start those are the
processes of installment so it's
deeply related to development and you're
not going to get it without development
but it's a different modality of the
psyche and similarly with
transcendence like that you don't get
any of them without the other ones
and my guess would be that in a very
rudimentary behavior it's harder to
piece them apart
and the more in cultured and and uh
civilized we get they can become
fractured and like i said even
for some of the modalities their
conversation and reply they can be
repressed
their reflection um so yeah i hear you
i hear that now that's very helpful and
it's a matter of understanding what
you mean by your terms and so i think
now i understand
yeah those parameters so yeah awesome
and it is we're saying a lot of what's
studied in
developmental psychology is culture
specific learning sequences
um and so piaget was attempting to get
at culture universal
learning sequences and then tomasello i
think really succeeded in doing that
and his new book just called becoming
human just a theory of ontogeny
it's really really good at getting at
this it's like you know what is the
actual universal
stuff of development and it's not any of
the particular models that were
are super popular like in the integral
scene and stuff it's a
deeper um kind of structure of
the nervous system and uh and
intersubjectivity actually joint
attentional
awareness and coordination of behavior
uh
cool so i'm glad that's clarified thank
you yes thank you very much
i've got a private question um
can you speak to monogamy versus
polyamory
in the context of the psyche modalities
so many of my friends are abandoning
monogamy as a part of moving
to a post-capitalist world and yet i see
a lot of
people suffering from limerence
whoa um
so this is of course an extremely
complex question
uh so a few things
you have to start off by talking about
how
the structure of the atomic family
and the notions of marriage especially
in
modern legal systems
are kind of messed up
like there's been a predation
that has been made on the family itself
by capital which is to say that the
possibility of having
a healthy nuclear family unit
has been made increasingly difficult by
the dynamics of capital and of course
as the kind of feminist marxists have
demonstrated capital put a particular
burden
and a particular role on the kind of
like
woman of the house who did all of this
stuff for free
that ended up contributing to getting
dad to work on time so he could
contribute to
capitalism uh so there's a dynamic that
we're
emerging from which is i think kind of
demonstrably
unhealthy and so many of us
were raised depends on your age here
were raised in households
where that was just obvious and so
there's this sense of like
marriage just as a bad idea because
the whole thing seems to be rigged
against it possibly
working well and
if you combine that with again that
legacy all the way back from freud
and reich told it in even stronger terms
this legacy of a very complicated
situation for sexuality itself within
western culture
that puts us in a position of basically
potentially looking back at the history
let's say for the last couple hundred
years of like
relationships and sexuality and and just
wanting to be
simply critical of it right same thing
can happen with critiques of capitalism
with critiques of the nation state with
critiques of
all that stuff is that it looks so bad
that you can just flip the script
well anything like that must be wrong
what's new must be something that's
completely
different so i actually get that initial
look
which would be to say something like
well monogamy is actually
simply an artifact of the patriarchy in
the capitalist world system
and that monogamy is entirely a
construct
which has no grounding in any ethical or
biological
reality so i can imagine constructing
that
for good reason based on near history
but i would also say just like we can't
simply throw
capitalism in the nation-state away
or modernity like that there were
dignities within modernity
uh that we also have to look at what is
very complicated and here's where the
mental psychology becomes
important a very complicated process of
ensoment
in particular that's tied up with
love relationships and
so i'll say a few things uh and then
i'll
first thing i'll say is that i'm not a
relationship expert
uh and uh it's a grain of salt
absolutely like this is not zach's like
10 steps to a healthy relationship
seminar this is like you know
shooting from the hip here but
a couple things one is that
the uh
as i mentioned you know
the victorian-era notions of sexual
repression that freud took as the basis
of his model
i think have been eclipsed by
these topics within the psyche that have
to do with death
in particular and the symbolization of
one's own
immortality in that same context
uh the movement from the
pre-tragic to the tragic to the
post-tragic uh
became like an essential set of stations
for identity development it's one of the
main things that's
the ceiling on the culture that's
stopping the resolution of the
adolescent identity crisis
right which is to say that to become an
adult
in this culture in this historical epoch
you have to be able to stabilize a
post-tragic
station of insolent and work from there
out through the modalities of
transcendence and
development and
this is a long roundabout way of saying
that
uh many
of the difficulties that occur in
monogamous relationships
will not be resolved by moving into a
polyamorous relationship
um that the dynamics of
insolvent uh and the dynamics of entre
and of transcendence that are possible
within relationship
um uh have
their own uh let's say dynamics
uh so you have to basically
you have to think about not just um
has the context in which i'm operating
changed you have to think about
have i changed right
so i mean this is like simple advice
but there's there's a
there is an unwillingness to engage
in the move from the pre-tragic to the
tragic
and then there's an unwillingness to
get out of the tragedy and into the post
tragic
right so at every time you turn one of
those stations
there's a there's a deep resistance and
so it is possible to use
uh the relationships you're in uh
and kind of like fix that make it so you
don't have to move from
pre-tragic to tragic or tragic to
post-tragic you delay the station's
shift
by rearranging relational dynamics
sometimes it may be what's called for
like i'm not saying you shouldn't get
out of relationships
but i am saying that uh
the only forms of polyamory that i've
seen
work have been with the
most mature people i've ever encountered
the people i have found most
wanting to engage in polyamory and
getting the most damaged by it
have been pretty tragic uh immature
people
and so i'm saying it quite bluntly
but the only way to deepen processes of
installment
is to make
commitments to others
in light of impending death
right that the the soul is living to die
and the soul isn't trying to escape
commitment and relationship
and insolent the soul's trying to go
deeper down
into the muck of this world
it's not seeking a transcendent
experience
through relationship the soul is
seeking deepening of emotional
intensities and obligation and
commitment
this is what the soul is doing so
you know the the image
of monogamy
and the image of polyamory that you're
holding
is extremely important and that those
images can move
through stations and that there needs to
be
a sense of what is that core image and
is it the image that i'm willing to be
in
when i die right
uh and so it's at that level
of commitment where human insulin takes
place
is that me and you till we're dead
right like i'm not saying it needs to be
with the partner
with now or that needs to even be with a
romantic partner
but i am saying that that level of
commitment right to the death me and you
were here
together in this together
no matter how bad it gets no matter how
bad it gets
that's what i'm in for the installment
process down and then
that's a commitment right and like
in the kind of late capitalist context
where the family's been preyed upon
they've made it impossible to make those
kinds of commitments to one another
right they've undercut the conditions
for the possibility of that kind of
commitment at a very basic level for
some people
so there's something extremely radical
about being able to make that
kind of commitment and so the closest
thing we have in our culture is
to that is marriage or family um
uh so that so that's a little bit there
so i'm not giving a strict answer but i
am saying that i do know from the level
of insulting to get to the post-tragic
you need commitment with others because
if you don't have that sense of
deeply co-inhabiting the same image of
the world
then you can't suffer you won't suffer
with them like the
there needs to be that depth of
connection
uh and that can be accomplished with a
with you know a non-monogamous structure
i'm sure
but uh i've seen
too much immaturity in that in that
domain to say yeah pursue that
like it it is very very difficult and
complicated
um to to find contexts in which you can
make the commitment of insolent with
somebody
so okay now i'm rambling we should
switch questions again i'm not a
relationship
expert so don't ask me
john davis had a question
thank you very much um when i was 12
years old i went to the library
and i researched homosexuality
and there was a consensus that
homosexuals
were doomed to prostitution
drug addiction that they could not love
um church state
and science all agreed
um and my conclusion was after
doing this deep research is
that i love jesus
and jesus would not do this to me
jesus was my first boyfriend
and then i
and there was a gigantic explosion
of renaissance of gay gay culture and we
were in a subculture
we
extremely creative and then all of a
sudden the aids epidemic hit
and sorry sorry
and creating self-help support groups
for people with aids
and i was uh doing reiki and i was
touching people
every day hours a day who were suffering
profoundly and i asked the question
very consciously does human love
transcend death that was a big
and i got some answers very direct and
very destabilizing also because there
was hardly anyone
that i could really um
direct my inquiry to um
but now i'm in this situation covet
uh which is very similar to the aids
epidemic except in many ways it's much
easier for me
i'm much older now than was in my
twenties when the aids hit
and my question now is or my desired
outcome i have a desire
i want to co-create
people who will have solved
the problems that we cannot solve
so uh and that's a
i do i think that's possible and i think
it's desirable
that we can create the conditions for
that future people
but we have to use our imaginations to
do this
and it's a very good big commitment so i
hope there's a
a useful question that's going to come
out of this inquiry and i just
uh want to celebrate zachary's work i
followed you for a long time and i
love this model and i find it extremely
useful and um
this is what's triggered by the memories
that have been triggered
by this inquiry today thank you very
much to
all of us
thank you john you you broke up a little
but i got parts of what was just a
beautiful
sharing and yet the image that sticks in
my mind is one of you
doing the hands-on work with people
suffering from aids and
i mean that's just such a it's such a
beautiful image and then in that work
you received
uh these transcendent insights into the
nature of love i mean
thank you for that thank you for sharing
that and
yeah that's that's exactly right and
that's a great example of the
forms of post-tragic commitment that i
was speaking to you know being with the
suffering ones
and in that context feeling
transcendence and
yeah so beautiful thank you thank you
benjamin you had a question
uh hey zach wondering could you give us
an example from your
own life i know you were just talking
about this a little bit but
an example from your own life of how you
worked with the movement from
pre-tragic to tragic to close tragic
thanks
uh totally um
yeah i mean i've shared this in in other
contexts uh but i've been a caregiver
um for my wife for about seven years now
who suffered a terrible iatrogenic
brain injury um from
a pharmaceutical drug and so that was
right at the end as i was finishing my
dissertation
um megan was stricken basically
bedridden and non-verbal uh
for a couple of years uh doctors
couldn't explain it
didn't want to explain it because it
happened from a pharmaceutical drug and
so i was her sole caregiver for that
time and she's still recovering there's
been kind of a miraculous recovery
uh but very very slow very very painful
so it was in that context and
specifically the transformations of my
image of self and other in relationship
that had that pre-tragic
too tragic than to post tragic and the
thing
with the post-tragic isn't like oh now
the tragedy's over
it's like oh now i know how to live
burning in tragedy
and so it was in fact uh being
overwhelmed by tragedy at one point
uh as it hit as it became clear a couple
years in that
how devastating the whole thing was
um that the
uh transformation of again
image um and the two-part process the
transformation of image allows for
if it's working right more symbolization
of symbolic immortality so i had to find
a way to metabolize
and this is why the alchemists talk
about the kind of like
container in which you do this kind of
dangerous alchemical transformative work
so i had to find a way to metabolize the
intensity of that
tragedy into new image and into new
forms of
symbolic immortality this is me
retrospectively
talking about what happened which during
the time was uh of course
um just you know
uh what it was and
and so that's that's what that that was
and
you know um megan
continues to recover uh and it's just
by far the strongest person that i know
um haven't given what's
given what she's been through and so you
know that deep in the sense of the
tragic and the post-tragic
and it with that sense also the
ontological reality of love
you know that it is a
force akin to a force of nature
and that when you are in a tragically
constellated situation
one of the things that's real like you
can punch it
so real is the bond of love
um and so as painful as it was
you know the intensity and the
and the depth of the experience of love
um
was it was was part of that process so
so it's a very personal sharing and like
i said there's
i did one podcast where i talked about
this
and talked about the development of a
crying practice
that i developed as a way to engage with
the transforming transforming image
of the tragedy that i was in because i
found that there were certain
images which is to say certain ways of
representing what i was living in
that were so difficult
that i was wasting energy pushing them
out of my awareness
i was trying not to see the actual
insolent situation that i was in
and uh i began working with his body
worker and
broke some stuff open and then began a
crying practice in which i
and again back to the alchemical imagery
i allowed the unbearable image to emerge
uh and so i became able to bear the
unbearable image
which is that notion of burning in the
tragedy it's not resolving
tragedy or fixing the tragedy which is
what everyone wants to do by the way if
someone's sick they want to fix it even
if they have no idea what's going on
they're like let me fix it you're like
you can't like
you can't fix it it's a [ __ ] it's a
tragedy
uh so that sense of allowing
through tears and again embodiment
the unbearable image to be born in your
psyche
uh that was really what got me through
and into the post-tragic was that
ability to
allow the full depth of the tragic
imagery
to emerge
and then to allow the physiological
process of encountering that image to
unfold which
in this case was just intense intense
grief
and so the processing of it up and
through
was critical if i hadn't figured out how
to do that i don't know what would have
happened
and so you know when you talk about
ensoment and stuff and this is why
you know the relationship thing that was
already mentioned is so key like
it's intense like in soulman is not
something you do
like in a peaceful meditation retreat
with
organic food and stuff like insomnia is
like tears
and snot and crying
and you know
yelling and um
pleading with god and a whole bunch of
stuff that's
that is very real to the human
experience
and and not like i think you know
megan's situation was extreme this was
extreme
tragedy but all human experience has
tragedy if you can undo the numbness
if you can step into a space of of
living in and towards death and living
down and deeper into the obligations
with those people who are immediate
around you in the image of your
installment
so that's yeah so
all right next question let's get some
easy questions in here guys
um david sweden you had an easy question
that's cruel all right hey zach um
the
um let me frame it this way one of the
symbols i asked a question about the
symbol the symbol of the
um mushroom cloud
is the transcendent possibly the
transcendent bridge
between collective developmental stage
to a collective ensolment stage
something of a and and the image is
powerful for me
um from multiple perspectives but one
thing of um
in my own kind of movement through this
i've seen
the sense of plato's cave is an
interesting
emers emerging from plato's cave
i think is symbolic of a neuron firing
right it's like an a neuron holds on to
the shadows on the internal wall of the
neuron trying to
maintain sense of what's happening until
it can't
anymore and must fire and when it fires
it releases the electric storage of the
chemical energy into
the into the network to get a new echo
of what's possible emerging from the
cave and returning
back to the cave with a new a fresh
image of what
new embodiment new insolent looks like
and so that and that and that
transitional movement
from human beings when we go through
deep developmental stage
shifts like adolescence or something
like that
i think is like that and then
collectively
i see the same thing possible for us as
human beings right is that so this
in a sense that that phoenix story of
crashing with all of the all of the last
straw that collapses the structure that
can no longer hold
the tension of experience and must
dissolve and re-pattern in a new
emergent way to to start the cycle over
again
so in thinking about that it seems that
it's possible
that the emergence of humanity
in our cognitive frame of doing this
is a kind of neuronal firing like that
in gaia's mind
that this cognitive frame that we have
is a is a
is a new thing which is tragic in one
sense it's the death
of the old model which we
don't want to have happen the grief and
suffering of that and yet the emergence
of something
new so it feels kind of like
um the possibility of something like
a new cambrian explosion of a different
kind
of mind infusing matter at another layer
that's a big question like i said that's
not easy but the sense of that
that cycle happening at various scales
along the fractal
and there's something like a
self-awareness as we
see our collective in the mirror
through the internet it's like oh my god
who are we
and the last grips of trying to hold on
to who we thought we were
it feels like we're on the edge of that
damn bursting
and letting go of who we thought we were
does that
fit in with there's some definitely some
interesting stuff in there
like two things i'll pull out one
the image of the mushroom cloud and the
image of the mushroom cloud
and the image of the earth from space
about roughly historically right so
and that notion of the image of the
earth from space like that was
mind-blowing when that dropped
on the culture um and then at the same
time the image of the mushroom bomb
roughly which is saying like we could
blow the whole thing up
that those emerged roughly the same
period
uh post world war ii uh
yeah there's something really
interesting there like i speak about
this
this process of planetization kind of
echoing tilian de chardon
and the notion of the new sphere it's
just kind of bringing to mind your
notion which is that
perhaps there's a particular historical
epoch during which time the species kind
of actually
planetizes and at that time it would
have both
total awareness of its planetary
situation and
the existential ability to end the
planetary situation
and that that would be something like
late adolescence realizing that oh my
god i'm a mortal human
i could die hopefully which is again one
of the resolutions of the adolescent
identity complex right is
realizing you're gonna die um so that
there's something like a shift that
we're in currently which is at the level
of humanity
the resolving or not of the adolescent
identity crisis right and so you could
also just
continue an increasingly risky behavior
as an adolescent
instead of resolving the crisis
and maybe end up self-terminating right
so
yeah so there is something there those
two images emerging kind of
reconstituting the human
psyche demanding that it has
self-awareness of its situation kind of
as an adult species responsible for
its host planet um and then the question
of whether
the internet's the thing that's going to
be the global brain
if it is right now it's
psychotic having a panic attack looking
at pornography
um and so there's a way in which the
internet as we know it now
uh certainly is not the internet that's
going to be the thing that allows us to
resolve the adolescent identity
crisis you know a main thing that's
happening
where i'm putting a lot of my attention
is fixing the informational ecosystems
that we all
live within so after that moment of
self-awareness
like the adolescent a little bit more
free prefrontal cortex comes on you have
a longer time arounds and you can take
more perspectives as that lesson
it's one of the most confusing times of
your entire life
um so there is kind of a lot of noise in
the
system right now culturally and the
question of kind of
what are the things that are the
maturational
challenges that we resolve or don't i
think is
is key so thank you for all that there's
some really interesting stuff in there
time for a couple more maybe
there's a dearth of questions in the
chat so um feel free to ask some more
questions everybody i
i have one more to relay us
um can you show us some concrete utopian
theorizing
on planet scale rites of passage
well
that's crazy uh well a few things so one
is that
what i was just describing now
was kind of a little bit of a planetary
scale right of passage
that the acquisition of you know
basically unlimited technological
violence
um and the ability to understand the
earth system
has an earth system uh
both suggest a threshold event at the
level of the collective psyche
um and so i would actually say that
you know we are currently
in a situation of having basically
postponed
confronting that rite of passage
so it was like we were put in a
situation of saying
hey human species you really need to get
mature extremely quickly
because of all the stuff that you just
built in the situation that has unfolded
uh and instead of saying wow i'm gonna
like
take a vision quest for a week and come
back like a new person
with a spirit name and ready to take on
responsibilities
um uh instead they were like cool man
i'm gonna keep playing
video games and stacking these papers uh
and that was
not the correct thing uh so this
question of
would it be possible to actually
uh orchestrate something like a
you know intentionally arranged or
planetary level
right of passage where we could become
more mature
um you know there's
one part of me that says well that's
this is inevitable
like you don't have to arrange it and in
fact any group attempting to arrange a
planetary scale anything right now
is probably one of the problems if those
groups exist
um which is to say like imagine
a pandemic spreading across the world
that was
you know became something like a
rite of passage for the entire planetary
civilization
right like if if you don't plan that
kind of thing and if you are planning
that kind of thing this is a huge
problem so
so what i'm saying is that the rite of
passage is
coming if not happening that it wasn't
intentionally designed that if it was
intentionally designed then it's not a
right of passing the right of
rite of passage that if you
try to arrange for tragedy
in order to move into the post-tragic
it's not a real tragedy
this is why the problem with ayahuasca
trips and all these things it's like if
you want to move
into the post tragic you have to engage
in actual tragedy
you can't arrange for a tragedy to
happen because you made it happen
you're controlling it uh
so the rite of passage for the human
species has probably been unfolding for
some time the concrete utopian
suggestion
is the one i always make which is that
we need educational resources
that are robust enough to allow us to
address this moment
of passage which is to say like
uh it's it's possible that um
getting a lot of weird feedback here are
those other people getting that
i don't know what that is nope stopped
sorry so
okay that that weird noise basically was
a sign for me to stop answering that
question
um so one more question
all right sam c had one question
thank you
hi zach um
the way i phrased my question and i
sent it to you let me see
um i don't get
why you say that soul is oriented to
death
is the acorn attracted to the stump
or the full canopy robust tree and you
get the image right the acorn theory of
insolent from hillman
and how i understand the model
on a personal level is that
you get on a quest for installment right
for the image you're born
with and that
image gives you the motivation
to build skills and get on the
developmental
scale and um
to find your niche into the
symbolic immortality right
so that's how i understand it and i see
this image the soul as an aspiration
what
reiki with corbin called the divine
double
right what is attracting you
to the fully alive version
of yourself right not the best version
of yourself of self-improvement but
what what what i said before about
this image and when i hear you
saying it's attracted to death i
understand the death of
some ego some social theater persona
but how is it like
how is it attracted to death the
annihilation
of the self like how can i um
make peace with with with what i see
and the attraction you're talking about
do you follow me yeah totally
it's very interesting because you're
right hillman's acorn theory
the metaphor perhaps falls short there
um
because it's also from hillman that i
get the notion that the soul
um images itself in relation to death uh
this is also hillman's notion and then
the way i understand it is basically
that
uh well it's essentially a reframing
viewer of what you said it's essentially
attempting to say something like um
you are living towards your death
that the death is in fact the telos
of life the death is in the problem
that the soul came here to figure out
the right way to die
um and so like to move into like
mythopoetic language like
why would you come here if it wasn't to
die
that's what happens here like if souls
are in some other realm where death
doesn't exist they just stay there they
can do tons of stuff
the whole unique thing about being here
is
limitation and death
and that image that you're moving
towards it's an image of your life
but it is in fact something you're
trying to kind of like do before you die
right you're trying to fulfill this
image you're trying to step into this
image
and the limiting factor and the thing
that drives
a lot of pathological archetypal
expression is that limiting factor
it's that notion that there's only so
much time here
that soul is a temporal insolment is a
temporal process of
moving down into the world
and in essence becoming
preoccupied with the
the finitude of it the finitude of it
that and this is what's different about
the experience of insulin the experience
of transcendence that
in the experience of transcendence you
move from your experience
up and out of the world into like a
liberated universal
experience right in installment you
experience
like you know this mug
right this mug my dad's mug right
this is a particular unique mug
there's like heart strings attached to
this mug this isn't a universal symbol
of
the like chalice that held the blood of
christ
no no this is my dad's mug right
and so that's the experience of insomnia
it's actually a deepening
of entanglement the feeling the
poignancy
of the uniqueness of the image that
you're in
which is to say that there will never be
another image like this image
that it is inimitable
and cannot be replaced
cannot be substituted or swapped out
under a common symbolic
umbrella right so that's kind of the
notion of that it's
my death that my soul is preparing for
uh you know zach stuff
very unique experience which needs to be
constellated
through this image to feel like the life
was
worthwhile that it made sense um
not that i found a way to be
transcendent within life
but that the lived life experience was
had the full potency of meaning
that the unique self was expressed and
death is the thing that
that's it's kind of the forcing function
on that
the the main source for this is actually
one of hillman's
best books which is suicide in the soul
this is i discussed this one with daniel
thorson and one of the first podcasts i
did with him
it's in there that he elaborates the
soul's obsession with death
and that suicide is
something like the soul's demand to see
god now
[Music]
and so yeah there's an intensity of the
souls
relation to death that's why it's so
pathological
because the unmet arc typical
impulse of the soul that clocks ticking
on that thing
you know if i'm not a musician in this
life i'm not a musician
says the archetype of the musician
within you
so okay beautiful thank you
this is fun so uh next time we will jump
just
straight into this kind of back and
forth and i invite
bringing you know case studies or
cultural artifacts or anything that can
uh
you know be grist for the mill
thank you zach for such an incredible
presentation and
uh thank you everybody i'm gonna tag
peter back in
and see you next week thanks guys
thank you nick um well i guess i'll just
plug a couple events today
we have um a pretty wild lineup
uh so in a half hour 12 p.m eastern time
alexander dugan most dangerous
philosopher in the world
writer of this book fourth political
theory will be at the stoa
feel free to come bring your tough
questions for the
mad russian and then uh derek jensen
4 p.m eastern time he's going to come in
talk about
his kind of philosophy world it's gonna
be a free associative conversation
and brett weinstein later today he's
gonna talk about his uni 2020
uh unity 2020 plan raven connolly will
be hosting that
lots of events on the website uh which
you can check out at the stoa.ca
if you'd like to support us the stoa
patreon account is right there that
being said uh
take nick back in for any closing
thoughts
no closing thoughts right now but thank
you peter and thank you everybody once
again
um hope to see you next week